Guide to the Ernst Bacon Papers, 1933-1986
Department of Special Collections
Ernst Bacon Papers,
1933-1986
Special Collections M0906
Bacon, Ernst, 1898-
1.25 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1986 and 1987.
Biography
Ernst Bacon was born in 1898 in Chicago, but moved to the San Francisco area in the 1920s and soon occupied a prominent role in the musical life of Northern California. Under his directorship, the San Francisco Federal Music Project achieved widespread popular acclaim, as the papers in the collection attest. Many Bay Area citizens and reporters supported Bacon in his conflict with the State and National Directors of the Federal Music Project. Bacon left San Francisco in 1938, the year following his dismissal, and proceeded to teach, compose, and direct in the East, receiving much critical acclaim. He returned to San Francisco in the 1960s and lived in the Bay Area for the remainder of his life.
Scope and Content
The majority of the collection relates to Bacon's tenure as the first San Francisco Director of the Federal Music Project, Works Progress Administration, 1935-1937. Included are correspondence (personal and professional), official project documents, concert programs, articles concerning the SFFMP, internal memoranda, and a variety of ancilliary material. Much of the correspondence and many documents record the conflict between Bacon and the State Director at the time, Harlè Jervis, and Bacon's subsequent dismissal as director. (87-039) Included in the collection is some of Bacon's personal correspondence from another source. This portion includes letters received by Bacon from the writers Janet Lewis and Henry Cowell, as well as Cowell's wife, Sidney, 1938-1986. (87-007 and 87-019) Additionally, the collection includes several scripts and musical scores from the musical comedy "Take Your Choice," written by Bacon, Phil Mathias, and Raisch Stoll. The musical debuted on December 2, 1936, and was originally performed by the San Francisco Federal Music Project, with Bacon directing the musical aspects of the show. (87-071)
Access Terms
Allen, Elizabeth.; Bacon, Ernst, 1898-; Berckman, Evelyn.; Bier, Allan.; Bietry-Salinger, Jehanne.; Boulton, Laura.; Clement, Ada.; Cowell, Henry, 1897-1965.; Cowell, Sidney.; Davis, George H.; Elson, Elizabeth.; Erskine, Morse.; Ferrier, Andre.; Fisher, Marjorie M.; Foote, Ralph M.; Frankenstein, Alfred.; Galkovitch, M.G.; Gunn, Glenn Dillard.; Hall, Jessie B.; Hayden, J. Emmet.; Hewes, Harry L.; Hopkins, Harry; Horgan, Paul.; Howell, Ruth.; Jervis, Harle.; Johnson, Mark E.; Jervis, Harle.; Jones, Isabel Morse.; Kasloff, Mischa.; Knight, Lucian W.; Lengyel, Cornel.; Lewis, Janet, 1899-; Liebling, George.; Luening, Ethel.; McAdoo, William Gibbs.; MacDowell, Edward, Mrs.; Mason, Daniel Gregory.; Mathias, Phil.; Moe, Henry Allen.; Morris, Lawrence.; Mullett, George.; Pattison, Lee.; Pazmor, Radiana.; Pettis, Ashley.; Pilling, Roy.; Potter, M.L.; Rodgers, Bernard.; Roosevelt, Franklin D., Mrs.; St. John, Edmunds.; Search, Frederick Preston.; Silva, Giulio.; Sinclair, Upton.; Skonhoft, Steen.; Sokoloff, Nikolai.; Stoll, Raisch.; Sullivan, Noel.; Ussher, Bruno David.; Wadsworth, Ralph G.; Weston, Brett.; Whatmire, W.B.; Williams, H. Glyn.; Wood, Charles Erskine Scott.; Woodward, Ellen S.; Wright, Cedric.; Zam, Maurice.; San Francisco Federal Music Project.; Works Progress Administration.; American literature--20th century.; Music--United States.; Prisoners as artists.; Composers--United States.
Container List
- Series I: San Francisco Federal Music Project Correspondence (specific sources, 1934-1939), 87-039
  - Bier, Allen (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bietry-Salinger, Jehanne (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Erskine, Morse (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ferrier, Andre (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fisher, Marjorie (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gunn, Glenn Dillard (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Haley, Mrs. Harry S. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hall, Jessica B. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hayden, J. Emmet (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hopkins, Harry (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Horgan, Paul (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jervis, Harle (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jones, Isabel M. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Luening, Ethel & Otto (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - MacDowell, Mrs. Edward (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - McAdoo, Senator William Gibbs (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Morris, Lawrence (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pilling, Roy C. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Search, Frederick Preston (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sinclair, Upton (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Skonhoft, Steen (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sokoloff, Nikolai (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ussher, Bruno David (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Wadsworth, Ralph G. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Wood, Charles Erskine Scott (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Woodward, Ellen S. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Wright, Cedric (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Series II: Ernst Bacon's Correspondence (general, 1933-1939 & n.d.)
  - Family (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Procuring Cottage at Inverness (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - General (1933-1936) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - General (1937-1939) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - General (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Drafts of letters, by Bacon (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Series III: San Francisco Federal Music Project Documents
  - "Project for Employment...," by Bacon & Gaston Usigli (3/34) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - WPA Request for Approval of Project Unit (9/36) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Confidential Salary Lists (10/36) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Typical Attendance Record (5/37) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Semi-Annual Report on Departmental Activities (6/37) (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Composers Forum-Laboratory (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Vocal Department Report (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Advisory Board (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Programs and Reviews (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Articles About the SFFMP by Bacon and Others
  - "The Federal Music Project," Cornel Lengyel (1937) (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "Resume of San Francisco Music Project," Bacon (1937) (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - "A Few Facts About the Federal Music Project," Bacon (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - "An Open Letter to the Federal Music Project of California," Bacon (1937) (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - "How is the Music Project Run?," Bacon (1938) (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - "Whispering Wires Need Psychic Powers," Marjorie Fisher (1937) (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - "In General... " (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Drafts of Articles by Bacon (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Drafts, Completed Articles, etc. by others (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Series V: Bacon's Scrapbook of the SFFMP
  - pp.13-14 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - pp.15-16 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - pp.17-18 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - pp.19-20 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - pp.21-22 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - pp.23-24 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - pp.31-32 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - pp.33-34 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - pp.37-38 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - pp.39-40 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - pp.45-46 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - pp.49-50 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series VI: Miscellaneous
  - SERA (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - State Symphony Orchestra of South Carolina (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Paebar Company (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - University of California at Berkeley (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series VII: Correspondence from Other Sources (1938-1986)
  - Cowell, Henry - 87-007 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cowell, Sidney - 87-019 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Lewis, Janet - 87-019 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series VIII: "Take Your Choice" Musical Comedy by Bacon, Mathias, & Stoll, originally performed by SFFMP - 87-071
  - Script (labeled "text") (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Script (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Script (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Score, "music left out of show" (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Complete Orchestra Score, Act 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Complete Orchestra Score, Act 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)